David Parrish
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
David Parrish papers
1940-2009, bulk 1964-1998
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Parrish, David
3.1 linear feet
The papers of Alabama photorealist painter David Parrish measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1940 to 2009, with the bulk of the material from 1964 to 1998. Parrish's career is documented through scattered biographical material; correspondence with galleries, publishers, art organizations, and friends; photographs of Parrish, his studio, and artwork; original artwork by Parrish and others; and printed material.
Provenance
The collection was donated by David Parrish in 2009.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of video recording requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
David Parrish (1939-) is a Photorealist painter living in Huntsville, Alabama.
Parrish was born in Birmingham, Alabama, and received his B.F.A. from the University of Alabama in 1961. He briefly moved to New York with plans to become a magazine illustrator, but was unable to find a permanent job. He moved to Huntsville, Alabama in 1962 and became a technical illustrator for Hayes International Corporation. Parrish continued painting at his home studio, moving away from the painting style he learned in school, and instead working on paintings derived from photographs. He left his job as a technical illustrator in 1971 and became a full-time painter. That same year he joined French & Company in New York as a gallery artist and had his first one-man show at Brooks Memorial Art Gallery in Memphis, Tennessee.
During the 1970s Parrish saw success as a first generation photorealist. He was represented from 1973 to 1976 by Sidney Janis Gallery, and then moved to Nancy Hoffman Gallery. In 1987 he joined Louis K. Meisel Gallery, and is still represented by them today. Parrish's motorcycle paintings became his early trademark, and during the late 1980s into the 1990s he painted complex, intricate porcelain still lifes of Marilyn Monroe, Elvis, and other pop culture icons. Parrish has shown his work in numerous group and solo shows, including many international shows, and is in the permanent collection of many museums.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Alabama photorealist painter David Parrish measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1940 to 2009, with the bulk of the material from 1964 to 1998. Parrish's career is documented through scattered biographical material; correspondence with galleries, publishers, art organizations, and friends; photographs of Parrish, his studio, and artwork; original artwork by Parrish and others; and printed material.
Biographical material consists of resumes, one folder of financial records, brief artist statements written by David Parrish, and two essays about Parrish's works written by others. Also included is a VHS video recording of an interview with Parrish conducted by Bob Williams in 1997 in conjunction with an exhibition.
Correspondence is primarily of a professional nature and pertains to Parrish's relationships with various galleries, publishers, and arts organizations. Of note is correspondence with galleries that represented Parrish's work including French & Company, Sidney Janis, Nancy Hoffman, and Louis K. Meisel, and correspondence with fellow artist Don Eddy. Also included is a small amount of personal correspondence with friends and family.
Photographs of David Parrish include one baby photo, official portraits, photographs of him in his studio, with family and friends, and at exhibition openings. Also found are photographs and slides of his artwork, including gallery installations and early photographs of the interior of Nancy Hoffman Gallery.
Artwork includes a sketchbook kept by Parrish while a student at the University of Alabama, several ink drawings produced during his employment as a technical illustrator at NASA's Marshall Space Flight Center, and a few sketches by others. Printed material includes exhibition catalogs, announcements, and posters, newspaper clippings, press packets, and other gallery publications documenting Parrish's career as an artist.
Much of the material in the collection includes recent annotations by Parrish describing his involvement with the projects and exhibitions, and identifying friends and colleagues.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1970-2000 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1964-2008 (Box 1, 5; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographs, 1940, 1960s-2009 (Boxes 1-2, 5; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Artwork, circa 1961-2002 (Boxes 2, 5; 5 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1962-2009 (Boxes 2-4; 1.5 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
French & Company (New York, N.Y.); George C. Marshall Space Flight Center--Officials and employees; Nancy Hoffman Gallery; University of Alabama--Students
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' studios--Photographs; Painters--Alabama; Photo-realism
Types of Materials:
Drawings; Essays; Interviews; Photographs; Resumes; Sketchbooks; Video recordings
Names:
Eddy, Don, 1944-; Hoffman, Nancy; Janis, Sidney, 1896-1989; Meisel, Louis K.; Williams, Bob-interviewer
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1970-2000, Series 1:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  This series contains scattered biographical material. Found here are four resumes, one folder of financial records including invoices and receipts, brief artist statements written by David Parrish, and two essays about Parrish's works written by others. Also included is a videocassette recording (VHS) of an interview with Parrish conducted by Bob Williams in 1997 in conjunction with an exhibition.
  - Address List, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "David Parrish Exhibition and Interview by Bob Williams" (1997), 1997-1998, (1 videocassette) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Resumes, 1970, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Resume for Louis K. Meisel Gallery, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Resume for Nancy Hoffman Gallery, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings by David Parrish regarding his artwork, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writings by Others regarding David Parrish artwork, circa 1973, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1964-2008, Series 2:; (Box 1, 5; 0.9 linear feet)
  Within this series is correspondence primarily of a professional nature and pertains to Parrish's relationships with various galleries, publishers, and arts organizations. Topics of correspondence typically concern exhibitions and other art related events. Of note is correspondence with galleries that represented Parrish's work including French & Company, Sidney Janis, Nancy Hoffman, and Louis K. Meisel, and correspondence with fellow artist Don Eddy. Also included is a small amount of personal correspondence with friends and family.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name with the exceptions of the first folder of the series which contains a birthday card to David Parrish from his wife Kay.
  - Card to David Parrish from Kay Parrish, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Allied Publications, Inc., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Art in America, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1969-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Alexander, Martha
    American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters
    Artists Against Nuclear Arms
    artSouth
    Awards in the Visual Arts
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1969-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Bamberg, Barrie
    Beilin, Howard
    Bernard Danenberg Galleries
    Birmingham Art Association
    Boise Art Museum
    Boston Corporate Art
    Bothwell, Joseph
    Brain Trust, Inc.
    Brooks Memorial Art Gallery
    Butler Institute of American Art
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1964-1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Cabral, Edward
    Capricorn Galleries
    Charman, Montague
    Cinecorp
    City of Huntsville
    Cleveland Institute of Art
    Cohen, Byron
    Costello, Irene
    Crandell, Mrs. George McCord
    Cystic Fibrosis Foundation
  - D-E, Miscellaneous, circa 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Dempsey, Jack and Debbie
    Eddy, Don
    Edith C. Blum Art Institute
    Emporia State University
    Escalmel, Francois
  - French & Company, Inc. (Nancy Hoffman), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Fagaly, William A.
    Federal Communications Commission
    Felt, Joanne
    Fisher, Mildred
    Fisher, Robert
    Flint Institute of Art
    Friedman, Marvin Ross
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1973-1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Galerie Des 4 Mouvements
    Grable, Beverly
    Gray, Michael (includes photograph of David Parrish)
    Green, John
    Greenville County Museum of Art
    Grisham, Betty
  - Huntsville Museum of Art, 1977-2003 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Harry N. Abrams, Inc.
    Haws, Mrs. Frank Phillip
    Heritage Foundation of Franklin and Williamson County
    Hochmann, J.
    Howe, Maureen
    Huntsville Symphony Orchestra
  - Journal of the American Medical Association, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    J. B. Lippincott Company
    Jordan, Rudy
  - Kaplan, Richard, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1969-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Kahan, Mitchell
    Kansas City Art Institute
    Kayo News
    Kissick, Kathleen
    Klein, E. L.
    Kinpit, Donald
  - Lawson, Tom, 1998, (Oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Louis K. Meisel Gallery, 1978-2008 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    La Medusa
    Les Editions De La Revue Moderne
    Linesch, Corinne Skinner
  - Maltby Family, circa 1975-2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Montgomery Museum of Fine Arts, 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Morgan Art Gallery, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Maralyn Wilson Gallery
    McDaris Exhibit Group
    Meiers, Mrs. J. Fred
    Mississippi Art Association
    Moreno-Lacalle, Peter
    Motor 16
    Mount Holyoke College
  - Nancy Hoffman Gallery, 1977-1985, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
  - National Museum of American Art, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Norek, Justyn, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - N-P, Miscellaneous, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    National Endowment for the Arts
    Orr, Marcus
    Philip Morris, Inc.
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Russell, Jeff, circa 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - R-S, Miscellaneous, 1978-1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Richards, Norm
    San Antonio Museum Association
    San Jose State University
    Sheinkopf, Paul R.
    Southeastern Center for Contemporary Art
    Spacex '89 Exhibition
    Sparks, Mrs. H. Claxton
    Stewart, Boardman
  - Schaul, Ellie, 1970-1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sidney Janis Gallery, 1973-1976, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Skipper, Mr. and Mrs. G. C., 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Society of Fine Arts, University of Alabama, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - T-V, Miscellaneous, 1977-2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Taylor, Jacqueline (Westpac Gallery)
    Uhlich, Robert Steadman
    University of Alabama
    University of Nebraska
    University of Tennessee
    Visual Publications
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    W. C. Bradley Co.
    Warren, Jo Anne
    Westbury Graphics
    Who's Who in American Art
  - Oversize Correspondence, Tom Lawson, 1998, (Oversized item from Box 1, Folder 25) (Box 5)
- Photographs, 1940, 1960s-2009, Series 3:; (Box 1-2, 5; 0.4 linear feet)
  Photographs of David Parrish include one baby photo, official portraits, photographs of him in his studio, with family and friends, and at exhibition openings. Also found are photographs of his artwork, including gallery installations and early photographs of the interior of Nancy Hoffman Gallery. This series also includes some photographs sent to Parrish from his friend and fellow artist Jeff Russell. Most of these photographs include annotations written on the back by Parrish.
  Photographs are arranged by subject matter.
  - Photographs of David Parrish, 1940, 1960s-circa 2000s, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 48-52)
    (Includes one baby photo, photos of Parrish with paintings, and official portraits)
  - David Parrish in His Studio, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family Photographs, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Openings, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibitions, 2004, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Nancy Hoffman Gallery, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jeff Russell's Studio and Summer House, circa 2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Artwork, "Jack" Painting in Studio, circa 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Artwork, circa 1980s-2009, (3 folders; oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1971-1990s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Oversize Photographs of Artwork, circa 1980s-2009, (Oversized items from Box 2, Folders 8-10) (Box 5)
- Artwork, circa 1961-2002, Series 4:; (Box 2, 5; 5 folders)
  Artwork includes a sketchbook kept by Parrish while a student at the University of Alabama, several ink drawings produced during his employment as a technical illustrator at NASA's Marshall Space Flight Center, and ink sketches by his mother, Jemima Parrish. Also found is a diagram sketched by Jeff Russell.
  - Drawings for Marshall Space Flight Center, 1960s, (Oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ink Sketches by Jemima Parrish, 2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Drawing by Jeff Russell, "How to Build the Frank Owens Stretcher," undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Oversize Drawings of Marshall Space Flight Center, 1960s, (Oversized items from Box 2, Folder 12) (Box 5)
- Printed Material, 1962-2009, Series 5:; (Box 2-4; 1.5 linear feet)
  Printed material includes exhibition publications, such as catalogs, announcements, and posters, newspaper clippings, press packets, and other gallery publications. Most of the material found here documents Parrish's career, and often he includes a handwritten note with the publication describing his involvement. Some catalogs and announcements are for exhibitions which Parrish attended but did not participate.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of material. Items within each folder are arranged chronologically.
  - Art Now Gallery Guide, 1981, 1993-2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Book, Contemporary American Realism Since 1960, Frank H. Goodyear, Jr., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1969-2008, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1962-1998, (9 folders) (Box 2, Folder 21-29)
  - Exhibition Posters, circa 1973-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Gallery Price Lists, 1998, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Magazines, 1966-1985, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Magazines, 1993-1995, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Museum Bulletins and Brochures, circa 1968-1990s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1967-1999, 2009, undated, (7 folders) (Box 4, Folder 3-9)
  - Press Packet for David Parrish: Photorealism, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Press Packet for The Detailed Image, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases, 1979, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Proofs for Exhibition Catalog, David Parrish at Louis K. Meisel Gallery, circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Tear Sheets for Louis K. Meisel Gallery, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Website Printouts, Louis K. Meisel Gallery, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 15)